Finding aid to the Margaret Hepburn Snyder papers SSC.MS.00194
Sophia Smith Collection
Margaret Hepburn Snyder papers
1940-1984
Sophia Smith Collection
Snyder, Margaret Hepburn, 1896-
SSC.MS.00194
1.667 linear feet (4 containers)
Margaret Hepburn Snyder became a charter member of Kenosha Hospital Auxiliary in 1940 and expanded her work to eventually become the Director of hospital volunteers at Kenosha Memorial Hospital, Wisconsin (1956-65). The collection documents her work at the hospital through an autobiographical manuscript, board meeting minutes, annual reports and newsletters, slides, speeches, and correspondence.
Biographical / Historical
Margaret Hepburn was born in Freehold, N.J. in 1896, the daughter and grandaughter of physicians. After graduating from Freehold High School she attended Smith College where she majored in sociology and music, and graduated in 1918. She married Cecil Denise Snyder of Freehold that same year. Her daughter Anne was born in 1920. In order to further Cecil Snyder's career, the family moved to Kenosha, Wisconsin in 1929. Margaret Snyder began volunteering at the Orthopedic School in Kenosha in 1931. In 1940 she became a charter member of Kenosha Hospital Auxiliary. In 1947 she expanded her involvement to the state level hospital auxiliary associations and by 1952 she was appointed to the Committee of Hospital Auxiliaries of the American Hospital Association. She also participated in the International Hospital Federation meetings in Sweden in 1956 and Belgium in 1962. Following the death of her husband in 1956 Margaret Snyder assumed a staff position at Kenosha Memorial Hospital, thus becoming its first fulltime Director of Volunteers. In this capacity she explored new approaches to patient care by expanding volunteer services throughout the hospital. After retiring from this position in 1965 Snyder remained active in hospital and church affairs in Kenosha for a few years before she relocated to Provo, Utah to be near family members.
Scope and Contents
The papers document her service to Kenosha Memorial Hospital (1940-65). Included are an autobiographical manuscript, "Those Old Homes as I Remembered Them" concludes with her 88th birthday; board meeting minutes, annual reports and newsletters which document the expansion of the hospital; slides illustrating the training of hospital volunteers; speeches given at hospital associations and national conventions between 1951-67; and correspondence consisting primarily of social notes and routine hospital business. The collection also contains the papers of state-level hospital associations, the International Hospital Federation, and the American Hospital Association.
Related Material
Additional material located in Student files, Smith College Archives
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Hospitals--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Volunteer workers in hospitals--History--Sources; correspondence; Writings; Organization files; scrapbooks; Speeches; photographs; Slides; American Hospital Association--History--Sources; International Hospital Federation--History--Sources; Kenosha Memorial Hospital (Kenosha, Wis.)--History--Sources; Snyder, Margaret Hepburn, 1896-; Snyder, Margaret Hepburn
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1950's-1960's; 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Writings
  - Speeches, 1950's-1960's (Box 1, Folder 2-8)
  - Newsletter, "Topics", 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Travel diary, Belgium, 1962-05 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Autobiography, Those Old Homes as I Remembered Them, 355 pp., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Kenosha Memorial Hospital
  - Volunteer Program
    - Annual reports, 1950's-1960's (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Handbooks for volunteers, 1950's-1960's (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Procedures, 1956, 1960, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Slides, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Auxiliary
    - History, 1940's-1960's, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - Meetings: minutes and announcements, 1940's-1960's (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Reports, 1960's, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Yearbooks, 1958-1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Building
    - Brochures, 1958, 1960,1967, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous memos and correspondence, 1960's, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1946, 1980, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Organizations
  - International Hospital Federation
    - Correspondence, 1960's-1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Committee reports, 1960's, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Membership lists, 1960's-1970's (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Pamphlets, brochures, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - News bulletins, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Fifteenth Congress, Chicago, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Sixteenth Congress, Dusseldorf, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - American Hospital Association
    - Annual meetings, 1958, 1959, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Annual conventions, 1951-1957 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Memorabilia
  - Scrapbook - articles, awards, clippings, programs, 1942-1965 (Box 4)